Today's דף daf officially it's 26 כ״ו. chaf vav. We will see
if we can get fully caught up, that's my goal. We pick
up however כ״ה עמוד א׳ chaf he amud aleph on the משנה.
mishna. So let's take a look. We had been dealing with the
theme of even if you're not supposed to marry, but if you
do you don't have to divorce. We had a fascinating discussion about
conversion and suspected adultery.
And now we look at we look at this next משנה mishna
within a following a similar type of a theme. המביא גט, ha-mevi
get, משנה mishna at the bottom of כ״ה עמוד א׳. chaf he
amud aleph. המביא גט ממדינת הים. ha-mevi get mi-medinat ha-yam. So you
think we were in גיטין. Gittin. Somebody brings a גט get from
overseas, which is the first משנה mishna in גיטין. Gittin. And for
anybody who's learned that, what do you have to say when you
bring a גט get from overseas? Charlie, what do you have to
say? בפני נכתב בפני נחתם. bifni nechtav bifni nechtam. You have to
testify that it was signed and sealed correctly. So let's say ואמר
בפני נכתב בפני נחתם, ve-amar bifni nechtav bifni nechtam, לא ישא אשתו.
lo yisa ishto. So the guy who came to testify that everything
was done correctly, he cannot marry the newly divorced woman. Okay, raises
certain questions about his reliability and veracity. Now let's say he says
הרגתי, haragti, I killed the husband. Okay, or הרגנו, haragnu, we killed
the husband. לא ישא אשתו. lo yisa ishto. Don't marry the wife.
Okay. Now of course what's bizarre here is that we're not at
all problematizing the fact that he just confessed to murder, but anyway
the point is that he's testifying that the husband is dead in
a quite dramatic way. And we also can't rely on that, or
let me rephrase this, in order to rely on that we cannot
allow him to marry the wife. If he marries the wife, it
casts questions onto his onto his veracity. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rebbi
Yehuda
omer,
הרגתי לא תנשא אשתו. haragti lo tinase ishto. I killed the husband,
he cannot marry the wife. הרגנו תנשא אשתו. haragnu tinase ishto. We
killed the husband, he can marry the wife. Exactly what the difference
is there, we will see in the גמרא. Gemara. But this is
other types of cases where there are secondary concerns. I mean we're
really quite digressing, right? We dealt with the case two brothers, or
two people I'm sorry, two people, two sisters, marry, you know
אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato or whatever it was. Not אחות... well I
think it was אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, etc. Don't marry, don't do
יבום yibum with both of them. And now we've gone into totally
different areas about don't marry. Don't marry because of suspected adultery, don't
marry because of a suspected affair, don't marry because of the testimony
about the suspected... well actually confessed murder, but don't anyway marry because
of the testimony that allows the wife to remarry. Right.
So that's
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, which is why the
משנה mishna is not saying let's go ahead and throw him in
jail.
But we mean by accident?
Right. Well it's not what it says. Okay.
Is it somehow? Yeah.
Okay, true.
It is true that להרוג le-harog is to kill as opposed to
לרצוח, lirtzoach, which is to murder. Anyway, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. טעמא דמדינת הים. ta'ama de-medinat ha-yam. The reason that
he cannot marry the wife is because he's coming from overseas. דעליה
קסמכינא de-alei kasamchina because we're relying on his testimony. אבל מארץ ישראל
aval me-eretz yisrael דלאו עליה קסמכינא de-lav alei kasamchina if he's delivering
a גט get and he's not and he's in ארץ ישראל eretz
yisrael but he doesn't have to testify that it was done correctly,
but he still is the person who's delivering it and we're not
relying on him, ישא אשתו, yisa ishto, he can marry the wife.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והמת. ve-ha-met.
How about the case when he says he died? Notice how the
גמרא Gemara rephrased the idea that I killed him. When he says
the husband died, דלאו עליה קסמכינא, de-lav alei kasamchina, we don't rely
on him. Now that's crazy, what do you mean don't rely on
him? You're totally relying on him, he said he saw the husband
dead. No, because we have rephrased what is the mechanics that's working
in that case. דאמר מר d'amar mar because we say the master
teaches אשה דייקא ומינסבא. isha dayka u-minsava. How can you rely on
one witness to remarry, one witness testifies the husband is dead? So
the גמרא Gemara really struggles with it and the answer the גמרא
Gemara gives is that the woman we trust the woman to investigate.
That since she knows that there are very, very harsh consequences if
it turns out the testimony was false and it turns out the
husband is alive and she remaried, we trust her investigation that follows
the testimony that the husband is dead to be to totally ascertain
that it actually is correct. So this is a quite radical גמרא.
Gemara. It's not just somehow saying that that supports the testimony. In
the end it's completely about her investigation that follows. So if that's
really true, then we're not really relying on him. דתני לא ישא
אשתו. de-tani lo yisa ishto. So why can't he marry the wife
if we're not really relying on him? In the case when he
testified the husband is dead, we're really just relying on the wife.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם ליכא כתבא הכא איכא כתבא.
hatam leka ksava hacha ikka ksava. There's still a big difference between
saying the husband is dead and just delivering a גט. get. Saying
the husband is dead you still are testifying to some facts, however
much that's bolstered or you know maybe even the bulk of it
is done by the woman's investigation, you still are testifying to facts
and there's a need to you know not question the veracity. Delivering
a גט get without saying needing to say that it was done
correctly... exactly if it was delivered in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, you
don't really need to testify to anything. The גט get itself testifies
to its own legitimacy. So you can if you're delivering it in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So that's the גמרא Gemara saying that's the
difference.
כדתנן kidtnan like we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, מה בין גט
למיתה mah bein get l'misa what's the difference between divorce and death?
Well for the husband it's a big difference, but anyway שהכתב מוכיח.
shehaksav mochiach. Okay, that the writ proves that everything is on the
up and up. You have a signed document and as long as
it's in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel that doesn't need external validation then
the person is really doing nothing other than delivering as opposed to
testifying the husband is dead the guy is still doing something.
Yeah maybe you mentioned this before I came in. Is there an
intrinsic reliability on a document that comes from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel
as opposed to...
Yeah, there's a general assumption that signed documents,
the גמרא's Gemara's phrase is
עדים שחתומים על השטר כמי שנחקרה עדותן בבית דין. eidus shehachatumim al
hashtar k'mi shenechkra edusan b'veis din. If you have a signed document
even if it's not the signatures haven't been what we would do
is we would get them what's that called notarized which is a
sort of what the בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam
is doing. But the גמרא Gemara says that על פי דין al
pi din even without notarization two signatures on a document is like
it's completely been delivered in court and the testimony is accepted and
it sort of proves itself. So only when it comes from חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz only have questions
about the reliability of the signatures I won't get into why but
anyway that's where it needs some external verification.
Like a notary you don't need any of that.
We will worry about when we get to מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin.
Okay מת אמרתי הרגונו לא תנשא האשה. meis amarti hargunu lo tinasei
ha'isha. So the גמרא Gemara says if you say however he died,
oh did I leave out the word מת? meis? I'm sorry. It
didn't start with I killed him. It started with he died. He
died, I killed him, we killed him, don't marry the wife. Again
the common denominator there is the witness is testifying that the husband
has died so don't marry the wife because that will cast aspersions
on the testimony. The גמרא Gemara says הוא ניהו דלא יסב איתתיה
hu nihu d'lo yisav iteseih he cannot marry the wife הא לאחר
תינשא ha l'acher tinasei she can marry a different man. Okay so
therefore even if he says I murdered the husband the only problem
basically it's acceptable testimony the point is that what's clear in the
משנה Mishnah is it's acceptable testimony that the husband is dead. The
only problem is don't marry the wife because that will then cast
questions on the testimony. But saying that you murdered the husband we're
still allowed to extract from that the fact that the husband is
dead like any normal עד אחד ed echad right people know this
הלכה halacha this is going to be a major part of יבמות
Yevamos that even though we always need תרי עדים trei eidin when
it's a question about a husband dying in order that the woman
should not be left עגונה agunah we actually allow to rely on
a single witness not only a single it doesn't matter man or
woman free person or slave very even hearsay testimony to testify to
the fact that the husband is dead. So what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is okay so the problem is he can't marry because
that will undermine the testimony but clearly the testimony is acceptable. Somebody
says I murdered the husband we extract from that that the husband
is dead and the woman can be remarried yes.
Suppose someone's testifying to his brother's death to get him out of
having to do יבום? yibum?
Meaning
does that free yeah I think so. Does that free the woman
from would that be yeah presumably yes.
We would be free you'd be obligated
obligated to do יבום yibum right sorry
good point.
Obligated to do יבום yibum right right right right right right. He'd
have to be testifying that the brother-in-law is dead and then it
frees the woman to marry somebody anyway.
That outweighs the fact that he's still being a witness in the
guy's death who died?
No but they're pointing out that that's the opposite of what you're
saying. It's not what do you mean?
What's he saying?
The fact that he has an obligation to do יבום yibum is
stronger than the fact that he could be...
apply יבום yibum to this case in the משנה Mishnah right? Anyone
that gave the testimony that I killed him so if he says
I'm not allowed to marry her...
oh
I understand.
What if it's his brother?
Yeah good point presumably he'd have to do חליצה chalitzah good point
actually to tie this משנה Mishnah into our מסכתא. masechta. Okay good
point if he's the brother then presumably he'd have to do חליצה.
chalitzah. Okay let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara okay הוא
ניהו דלא יסב איתתיה הא לאחר תינשא hu nihu d'lo yisav iteseih
ha l'acher tinasei she can marry another man ואמר רב יוסף v'amar
Rav Yosef Rav Yosef says if somebody comes and testifies פלוני רבעני
לרצוני ploni revani l'retzoni a certain man a man testifies that another
man what did I skip a line? לאונסי l'onsi I said לאונסי.
l'onsi. Another man had sex with me against my will so he's
basically testifying look this is obviously these גמרות Gemaras are obviously very
hard to read in the
contemporary whatever given just contemporary attitudes towards gay
men and women but the גמרא Gemara is clearly dealing with it
through a biblical perspective and this is... This is a חיוב מיתה
*chiyuv misa*, this act, and therefore the question is somebody who goes
ahead and testifies to it. So if he says it was against
my will, so he’s not saying that he himself did a sin,
he was forced, okay, he was raped by another man. So, but
he’s testifying that the other man did this act of did this
act. הוא ואחר מצטרפים להרגו *Hu ve'acher mitztarfim le-hargo*. He and another
person can come joint witnesses to testify against against this man and
for for the to execute him in the court for this act.
Okay, so therefore even though he was involved, if it was against
his will, if he was raped, he does not get excluded. However,
if he says ברצוני *birtzoni*, it was done willingly, I did it
willingly, I was a willing participant, then רשע הוא *rasha hu*. He’s
saying that he himself was sinning and therefore he’s a רשע *rasha*,
and what’s האמרה *ha-omra*, אל תשת ידך עם רשע להיות עד חמס
*Al tashet yadcha im rasha lihyot ed chamas*, he can’t combine with
another person to testify. He’s excluded himself from testimony because he said
he was a willing participant. So the relevant point about this is
and this is a סוגיא *sugya* of פלגינן דיבורא
*palginan dibura*. Can we split his words? Take the part of the
testimony that is not about himself and still use it. So here
we see we can’t. If he testifies that he was involved in
an act, we cannot say well, okay, you can’t testify against yourself,
but we’re going to bracket that and only focus on the part
of the testimony that applies to somebody else. No, you in the
process have testified that you’re an invalid witness, that you’ve done the
sin and therefore it invalidates you as a witness, so we have
to throw the whole testimony out. So that’s true in that case,
it should be true in this case. Somebody basically testifies he murdered
the husband. Okay, you’re basically according to you, you’re an invalid witness.
We can’t accept the testimony. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now, now
the obvious answer would be that’s the first case is to prosecute
somebody in court, right, in order to apply the death penalty. There
maybe we have very exacting standards. Here we’re dealing with testifying the
husband is dead. Like what we’re telling you, even one witness, we
don’t distinguish man or woman, free person or slave. So there maybe
we are willing to do a פלגינן דיבורא *palginan dibura* and extract
the relevant data and bracket the question of, you know, of the
fact that according to your own testimony you’re a murderer. Yes, David.
I'm assuming is this in the context of a בריסק *Brisk* type
of solvation? Is that the case or is that splitting something that
came before his analysis? This idea that you just described about
פלגינן דיבורא *palginan dibura*, yeah, that’s not really related to the whole
בריסק *Brisk* approach, that’s already straight in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay,
and it doesn’t sort of work, it’s not like it would directly
about the type of categories that they בריסק *Brisk* has created. וכי
תימא שאני עדות אשה דאקילו בה רבנן *Vechi teima shani edus isha
d'akeilu ba rabanan*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it, alright, maybe
this testimony about the wife and therefore the Rabbis are lenient about
it. Okay, ואמר רב מנשה *va'amar Rav Menashe*, but רב מנשה *Rav
Menashe* says, גזלן דדבריהם כשר kosher לעדות אשה *gazlan de-divreihem kasher le-edus
isha*. A rabbinic גזלן *gazlan*, like you know gamblers let's say, that
are rabbinically invalid as witnesses, they can testify relating to the wife.
Okay, however, גזלן דדברי תורה Torah. פסול לעדות אשה *gazlan de-divrei Torah
pasul le-edus isha*. So a biblical somebody who is a though again
we have a wide range of witnesses that are accepted, not somebody
who is biblically invalid. Now again it’s interesting, a woman is biblically
invalid but this person is biblically invalid
for reasons of some type of sin and transgression. So that person
is invalid. Now of course you could also make the distinction which
תוספות *Tosafos* raises, if somebody there are two types of ways of
invalidating a witness. One is because of a sin relating to money
where basically the point is he’s basically telling you he’ll sin for
money. So basically he’s telling you his testimony can be bought. Okay,
so that type of a person you understand why you don’t want
to testify about the woman’s dead husband because basically you’re afraid that
his testimony could be bought. There’s another type of a person that’s
invalid because they’re a סתם *stam* sinner. They eat חזיר *chazir*, נבילה
לתיאבון *neveila le-te'avon*, okay?
So why is that type of a person necessarily invalid for עדות
אשה *edus isha*? Not as obvious. Alright, so תוספות *Tosafos* anyway raises
that question. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here does not distinguish. So it
says according to this person’s testimony he’s a murderer. Alright, and
therefore how could we accept him for עדות אשה *edus isha*? Again
there you could still distinguish that maybe only somebody who’s biblically invalid
because of external testimony not because of a person’s own confession. Alright,
but this is still what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is bothered. By
his own confession he’s a murderer, he should be invalid for this
testimony. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, נימא רב מנשה דאמר כרבי
יהודה Yehuda. *neima Rav Menashe d'amar k'Rabbi Yehuda*. Maybe רב מנשה *Rav
Menashe* says like רבי Rebbi. יהודה Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*? One minute, ah
because רבי Rebbi יהודה Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
says that if he says I’m the murderer we don’t accept the
testimony. So maybe that רבי Rebbi. יהודה Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* or the
other way of saying it is that the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*
rejects this and allows a biblically invalid witness to be a to
be a witness. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
אמר לך רב מנשה *amar lach Rav Menashe*, רב מנשה *Rav Menashe*
would say... ואין אדם משים
עצמו רשע *ve-ein adam mesim atzmo rasha*.
A person is close to himself, he's, you know, his own best
relative, his own closest relative, and therefore he does not make himself
into a רשע *rasha*, which is basically a way of saying פלגינן
דיבורא *palginan dibura*, that we do split his testimony, and therefore we
say the testimony that relates to you yourself, we throw it out,
because you're now not allowed to testify against yourself. Okay. The only
time you can testify against yourself, like confession doesn't work in הלכה
Halacha *halacha*. It only works in monetary areas. You can admit to
a debt, you can admit to a monetary obligation, but if you
admit to a crime that is not acceptable, you know, which is
about מיתה *misa* or מלקות *malkos* or whatever, that is completely irrelevant.
We need external testimony. So therefore, the part that you testified against
yourself that you're a murderer is irrelevant and we throw it out,
and we only accept the part that the guy is actually dead.
Of course, well then why don't we say that about the other
case in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*? Where the גמרא Gemara? *Gemara* starts
with, right, about the case of rape and so on? So take
a look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says like this.
מר
*Mar* says like this. Oh, you know, let's not do רש"י Rashi.
*Rashi*. Let's continue the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
itself clarifies. So לימא רב יוסף דאמר כרבי יהודה Yehuda *Leima Rav
Yosef de-amar ke-Rabbi Yehuda*? So how about רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*? רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* is the one that spoke about the case of
rape, and he says that you don't split the words, that you
only take the part, that you have to throw out the whole
testimony. And we're saying basically you split the words. So maybe רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* has to go like רבי יהודה Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
says you don't accept the testimony when he says I'm a murderer.
So אמר לך רב יוסף *Amar lach Rav Yosef*, no, אנא דאמרי
אפילו רבנן *Ana de-amri afilu Rabbanan*. Again, I can work with the
רבנן *Rabbanan*. So again, how is this different? Right? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, ושאני עדות אשה דאקילו בה רבנן *Veshani edus isha
de-akilu bah Rabbanan*. Okay. And but we're more lenient here because it's
testimony about the woman getting remarried, so we don't have the normal
same standard where I'm saying that you would throw out the whole
testimony. רב מנשיה דאמר כרבי יהודה Yehuda, *Rav Menashia de-amar ke-Rabbi Yehuda*.
But it's רב מנשיה *Rav Menashya* who says like רבי יהודה Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda*. Okay. Because רב מנשיה *Rav Menashya* is the one that
says that biblically you throw it out, so even by עדות אשה
*edus isha* I wouldn't say that... I would say by עדות אשה
*edus isha* you accept it. So it's interesting is that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* sort of takes two halves of the answer and it
could have combined the answer. What it basically says is the following.
רב מנשיה *Rav Menashya* who says that we throw out biblically invalid
testimony for עדות אשה *edus isha* or biblically invalid witnesses for עדות
אשה *edus isha* would basically say, I don't agree with רב יוסף
*Rav Yosef*. I say we split... if somebody testifies against themselves, we
only take the relevant part about the other person, not about themselves.
So I disagree with רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. And therefore, in this
case, we can take the testimony about the husband. Even though I
would say that, you know, normally you have to throw out a
biblically invalid witness for עדות אשה *edus isha*. רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*
who says we don't split the testimony would say, I don't agree
with רב מנשיה *Rav Menashya*. I say that even a biblically invalid
witness can work for עדות אשה *edus isha*. And therefore even a
guy who says he's a murderer we can accept it for עדות
אשה *edus isha*. Of course you could have had something that says
everybody agrees. Everybody agrees that when you combine the two facts: number
one, it's only עדות אשה *edus isha*, and number two, we have
the possibility of splitting the words, in that case, in that scenario
we'll do that. You might hold that when it's only one of
those it's not acceptable, but when those two are combined we actually
will. So that's the case in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. According to
the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*, even if he says I am the
murderer, we accept it. Why wouldn't we normally throw something like that
out? So either because no, in a case of testimony about a
husband we won't throw it out, or because no, we won't throw
those things out because we'll split the words. Or what I'm saying
is let's say both, because it's a case about the woman remarrying,
that will allow us to split the words and only accept the
relevant part of the testimony, not the irrelevant part that he's the
murderer. Yes.
I don't understand. You're saying he's a biblically invalid witness? But basically
you're saying he's a valid witness. Correct. But it's semantics.
No it isn't. We will not accept the biblically invalid witness when
we have external testimony, but we will accept it... but if it's
due to your own testimony then we don't believe... then we don't
accept the fact that you're an invalid witness. Okay. Or, right, so
that's the...
And then if he says I'm the שליח בית דין beis din
*shliach beis din*, then they'll be okay to marry him, right? In
other words, he was committed in a capital court and I killed
him in self-defense.
Yeah. So that's not even the issue.
That I killed him in self-defense.
Yeah, that's what Michael's saying. Then that's not an issue at all.
That's not an issue at all. That doesn't raise his status as
a רשע *rasha*. Okay. So, okay. הרגתיב, הרגנוהו, תנשא *Haragtiv, haragnuhu, tinasei*.
מאי שנא הרגתיב ומאי שנא הרגנוהו *Mai shena haragtiv u-mai shena haragnuhu*?
So we sort of pointed out that רבי יהודה Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*
in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* who makes a distinction is bothered by
not accepting the testimony when he says that he himself... that he
himself is a רשע *rasha*. Okay. So then what's the difference between
he says I murdered her or we murdered him? Even if it's
a we murdered him, you're still a רשע *rasha*, you were part
of a murder. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רבי יהודה
Yehuda באומר אני הייתי עם הורגיו *Amar Rabbi Yehuda be-omer ani hayiti
im horgav*. It doesn't mean I murdered him. It means I was
there, I was part of the group, I was part of the
planning, I drove the getaway car, okay, but I didn't actually murder
him. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... והתניא אמרו לו לרב יהודה
מעשה בליסטיס *V'hatanya amru lo leRav Yehuda ma'aseh belistis* or ליסטים *listim*
we pronounce it, but I know, but it's really ליסטיס *listis*, it's
really the singular, אחד *echad*. Anyway, story with a certain bandit שיצא
להרג *sheyatza lehoreig* במגיזת קפוטיקיא *be'migizat Kapotkia*, he was going out to
be killed in this place, presumably by the court. ואמר להם לכו
אמרו לאישה שמעון Shimon בן כהן *Ve'amar lahem lechu imru le'ishah Shimon
ben Kohen*, go tell the wife of שמעון Shimon בן כהן *Shimon
ben Kohen*, אני הרגתי את בעלה *ani haragti et ba'alah*, that I
murdered. So here it was, it was like a confession he makes
right before he's executed. Go let the wife know of שמעון Shimon,
בן כהן *Shimon ben Kohen* I killed her husband. He's worried about
trying to make up, you know, make some amends right before he
dies. ובבואו בכניסתי ללוד *uv'vo'o bechnisati l'Lud* when I was going into
Lud, ואמר בכניסתו ללוד *ve'amar bechnisato l'Lud* or when he was going
into Lud. והשיאו אשתו *Ve'hasi'u ishto* and they married off his wife.
So here you see that the guy is ממש *mamash*, he's a
murderer, and we still accept the testimony. And this is not just
his own saying he's a murderer, he's being taken out to be
executed, okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says משם ראיה
*Misham rayah*? So anyway, so they said this to רב יהודה *Rav
Yehuda*, don't you see that somebody can, what do you call it,
that we can accept the testimony of somebody even if he says
he's a murderer? So he says, אמר להם משם ראיה *Amar lahem
misham rayah*? You want to bring a proof from that? באומר אני
הייתי עם הורגיו *Be'omer ani hayiti im hargav*. He wasn't saying that
he was the murderer. He was saying, I was there, I was
part of the group, but not that I literally did it myself.
So you see, so you see that רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says,
yeah, so you see that רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* though says that
the case that רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* accepts is when he says
he was part of the group and not when he did it
himself. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, וליסטיס קתני *V'listis
katani*.
It says that he was a bandit. Okay, שניתפס על ידי ליסטיות
*Shenitpas al yedei listiyut*. So fine, he was captured for banditry, but
that doesn't necessarily prove that he was a murderer. It says והיוצא
להרג קתני *V'hayotze lehoreig katani*, he's going out to be executed, so
clearly he's a murderer. So how could anybody accept the testimony? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, no, בית דין beis din. של עובדי
כוכבים דלא דייקי וקטלי *Beit din shel ovdei kochavim delo dayki vekatli*.
That's the non-Jewish courts, they don't necessarily have sufficient evidence, they'll just
kill based on types of suspicions. Okay, but אין הכי נמי *ein
hachi nami*, everybody would agree that if he was a convicted murderer
by a בית דין beis din. *Beit Din*, we couldn't accept the
testimony, at least according to what we said before about רב מנשיה
*Rav Menashya*, that we don't accept testimony of, of, you know, of
רשעים *resha'im*, of biblically invalid witnesses, even for the testimony about the
husband. Okay, רב מנשיה *Rav Menashya* might argue, others might argue on
that, say we accept everybody for witness of husband. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is saying is both תנא קמא *Tanna
Kamma* and רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* assume that if he's clearly a
רשע *rasha*, clearly a murderer, we don't accept the testimony. ותנא קמא
*Ve'Tanna Kamma* says, so if he testifies against himself, it's irrelevant. רב
יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says, no, if
he testifies against himself, it is relevant, we don't accept the testimony,
but we'll accept it if he says he was part of the
group even if he wasn't, as long as he wasn't actually the
murderer himself. Yeah. He's being executed though not על פי *al pi*
his own testimony against himself?
No, I don't, who knows, maybe he is, but it's being done
by the non-Jewish court, so it's not relevant, it's not sufficient evidence
for us to halachically define him as a murderer, yes.
Unless he like is, like, a, not like, you know, his mental
health, if he's condemning himself to like imprisonment or death, can't you
say that, oh, so he probably, if he's saying he did it,
he probably did it if he's going to get punished? Was there
no legitimacy to that logic?
Well, first of all, the רמב"ם *Rambam* says that the reason you
don't accept confessions is because you might assume that people confess for
a whole wide range of reasons, not necessarily because they've done it,
and maybe because they're also not so mentally well and whatever other
possible reasons, right. And, so but
anyway, but the point is that what you're saying is exactly what
the conclusion is according to the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*. You extract
the facts without necessarily condemning him as the one who did it.
Yeah, so that is what the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* says. Alright,
so let's take a look at the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. החכם שאסר
את האישה *He'chacham she'asar et ha'ishah*. So that was interesting because those
were cases where you're not supposed to marry, but of course the
hanging question is, because the scene here is, reasons not to marry
and if you do marry do you have to then get divorced?
So what that משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* was lacking was the final line.
What happens if the guy who delivered the גט get *get*, or
the guy who said the husband would die, did marry the wife?
What do we do then? Okay, so that'll come up in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but that obviously is the scene here and it's
funny that it didn't end with that. And now we get to
another case of not supposed to marry. החכם שאסר את האישה בנדר
על בעלה *He'chacham she'asar et ha'ishah b'neder al ba'alah*. So basically, a
woman came to a חכם Chacham *chacham* and said, I just made
this vow and my husband is telling me that if I can't
get it annulled he's going to divorce me and the, or maybe
she didn't say that, but okay, anyway, and the חכם Chacham *chacham*
says, looks at it, says no, I'm sorry, there's no way we
can annul the vow, there's not a, there's not any opening here.
Okay, so then the woman gets divorced and then the חכם Chacham
*chacham* basically goes ahead and proposes marriage to the woman. Okay, so,
so that you're not supposed to do that. Okay, so we need
a משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* to teach us. החכם שאסר את האישה בנדר
על בעלה *He'chacham she'asar et ha'ishah b'neder al ba'alah*, based on his
vow, she became forbidden to her husband, it's actually even worse than
I said. Okay, because I said that her husband said he was
going to divorce her. Here it says that the נדר neder *neder*
actually forbids her to her husband, so basically she made herself, like
she basically said, you know, it's if she said, I am forbidden,
you know, to my husband. for like sex with me is forbidden
against my husband, which you can sort of do with a נדר.
neder So really the result is that it's impossible for her and
her husband to continue living together, so it's even a more extreme
case. הרי זה לא ישאנה, Harei zeh lo yisa'enah, he can't marry
her after they get divorced. מיאנה או שחלצה בפניו, Mi'enah o shechaltzah
bifanav, now let's say he was involved in another thing that got
a woman separated from her husband or the man she was connected
to. Basically he was part of the בית דין beis din that
supervised she was a minor that was married to this guy through
the brothers and mother, so she had the right of verbal refusal,
מיאון, mi'un, but you need that in front of a בית דין.
beis din He was part of that בית דין. beis din Or
she did חליצה chalitzah to her brother-in-law and he was part of
the בית דין beis din. that observed that. So in that case
ישאנה, yisa'enah, in that case he can marry her afterwards מפני שהוא
בית דין, mipnei shehu beis din, because it wasn't him himself, he
was part of a בית דין beis din and therefore we won't
necessarily impugn him, there were two other people that were there as
well. Of course the other thing you could say is that those
are cases that don't require the same degree of discretion, right? The
case about נדר neder requires a lot of discretion. Now everything requires
some discretion, are you going to invalidate the חליצה, chalitzah, invalidate the
מיאון, mi'un, there's a technical problem or whatever, but not the same
degree. But the משנה Mishnah doesn't focus on that, it focuses on
the fact that it was not him acting alone. Of course whatever,
I think they've done these sociological studies I'm sure Charlie could tell
us all about that in where in like between like the ways
that group operates and individuals
operate and anyway basically somebody who knows what he's doing can manipulate
a group to come to a decision himself and in certain ways
even hide the fact that he's responsible for it.
Right. Anyway, but okay, the משנה mishna is saying either there's less
to genuinely be concerned about or less to be concerned about in
terms of appearances. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: ההיא
דתירא ישאנה, Hahi d'tira yisa'enah, so from the משנה mishna. we see
that if the חכם chacham התיר hatir freed her from the נדר
neder and then the husband dies or divorces her for some other
reason, he can marry her, which makes sense. Okay, so במאי עסקינן?
b'mai askinan? So what's the case? אילימא בחד, ileima b'chad, if it's
a single person annulling the vow, חד מי מצי מתיר, chad mi
matzi matir, how can a single חכם chacham release somebody from their
vow? והא אמר רב אמר רבי חייא או אמר רבי חייא בר
אבין אמר רב, v'ha amar Rav amar Rabbi Chiya o amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abin amar Rav, תנא התרת
נדרים
בשלושה, tana hataras nedarim b'shlosha, you need a בית דין beis din,
for התרת נדרים hataras nedarim as we all know on ערב ראש
השנה. Erev Rosh Hashanah. ואלא בשלושה, v'ela b'shlosha, okay fine, it was
part of a בית דין. beis din So מי חשידי? mi chashidi?
So if you have three people doing it, why would any one
of them be suspect? You're not operating on your own. והתנן, v'hatnan,
the end of the משנה mishna. says: מיאנה או שחלצה בפניו ישאנה
מפני שהוא בית דין, mi'enah o shechaltzah bifanav yisa'enah mipnei shehu beis
din, that if it's part of an act of בית דין beis
din, then you can marry afterwards. So the גמרא Gemara says: לעולם
בחד, l'olam b'chad, we are dealing with a case of one, וכדאמר
רב חסדא אמר רבי יוחנן ביחיד מומחה, v'chadamar Rav Chisda amar Rabbi
Yochanan b'yachid mumcheh, that actually even though we need three for a
התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim, you can also do it with a single
person if he is an expert, if he is a מומחה. mumcheh.
What exactly qualifies מומחה mumcheh I'm not going to go into, but
you can have somebody who's a real expert. Three people who are
laypeople can do it, one person who is an expert. הכא נמי
ביחיד מומחה, hacha nami b'yachid mumcheh, so that's the case here. So
yes, the case in the משנה mishna is where it is a
single חכם chacham who is doing it. Again, you could also say
it's the difference of degree of discretion, but that is not where
the גמרא Gemara is going. מיאנה או שחלצה, mi'enah o shechaltzah, but
if it's part of the בית דין, beis din one of the
members of the בית דין beis din, can marry the woman. טעמא
דבית דין הא בתרי לא, ta'ama d'beis din ha bitrei lo, the
reason is it's a בית דין, beis din, but if it was
a case where you needed two, so then maybe since he's a
fifty percent of the vote maybe in that case he cannot marry
the woman. Now what would be a case of two? מהיכא מהא
דתנן, mahyacha meha d'tenan, well let's take a look. Case in the
משנה, mishna actually דתניא, d'tanya, בריתא. braisa. עדים החתומים על שדי
מקח, edim hachatumim al s'dei mekach, you have two witnesses on a
field of a sale document that something was sold. על גט אשה,
al get ishah, or on a woman's writ of divorce. לא חשו
חכמים לדבר זה, lo chashu chachamim l'davar zeh, the sages were not
concerned. What were they concerned about? Can one of the witnesses of
the גט get remarry the wife? Can one of the witnesses on
a sale of the field go ahead and purchase the field? So
there you could say maybe the גט get. is a forgery and
you're doing it so you can remarry the wife. Or the writ
of sale is a forgery and you're doing it so that the
field can be sold to a third party who's agreed on this
whole scheme and will sell you the field. No, we're not concerned.
So you see even when there are just two, anytime you're not
operating alone we're not concerned. So the גמרא Gemara says: so what
is it? Do you need two or do you need three? So
the גמרא Gemara says: no, היא גופא קמשמע לן לאפוקי ממאן דאמר
מיאון בפני שנים קמשמע לן מיאון בגימל. hi gufah kamashma lan le'apokei
miman d'amar mi'un bifnei shnayim kamashma lan mi'un b'gimmel. So
the
גמרא Gemara is saying you're right that the משנה mishna isn't, בית
דין beis din is not needed, really anything more than one. In
passing it's pointing out that it is a בית דין, don't think
that מיאון mi'un only requires two, מיאון mi'un requires three, it does
require a בית דין, but in the end of the day it
doesn't need a בית דין to allow remarriage, even two as long
as you're not
acting independently remarriage would be allowed. Okay. איבעיא להו כנס מהו שיוציא?
ibaya lehu knas mahu sheyotzi? So now they raise the question: כנס
מהו שיוציא? knas mahu sheyotzi? Finally, that seems to be the reason
these משניות mishnayos were here, but we didn't have the end line.
All these cases of not remarrying in the case of the חכם
chacham with the נדר neder, or in the case of the סופני
נכתב sofani nechtav or the husband is dead. What happens if they
got married? Can you remarry? Now רש"י Rashi says it's talking about
if you look at the רש"י, Rashi, חכם והמביא גט קאי. Chacham
v'hamevi get kai. It's talking about both of the earlier cases, okay,
about the case of the חכם Chacham and the נדר neder and
the guy bringing the גט. get If you look at the little
אלף alef in the גרא, Gra, he says, וכן כתב הרמב"ם והשולחן
ערוך אבל רשב"א כתב דלא קאי רק אמתניתין זו
דחכם, V'chein katav haRambam v'haShulchan Aruch aval Rashba katav d'lo kai rak
amatanitin zo dechacham, but not on the case of מביא גט. mevi
get. So there's some question which is the scope of the גמרא's
Gemara question of what's the בדיעבד b'dieved story, just on this משנה
mishna. or on the previous two משניות. mishnayos. Anyway, let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, what's the happen if they actually got
married? So רב כהנא אמר כנס מוציא, Rav Kahana amar kanas motzi,
you have to divorce. רב אשי אמר כנס אינו מוציא, Rav Ashi
amar kanas eino motzi, you don't divorce. Of course it seems that
the sense of these משניות mishnayos is don't divorce.
It only mentioned one case so far, the case of adultery, right,
which was very weighty, which it was a divorce. But anyway, here's
a debate in these, in these cases where it's not spelled out.
So תני ליה לרב זוטי בדבי רב פפא כדיבי אמר כנס אינו
מוציא. Tani lei l'Rav Zuti b'debei Rav Papa k'debei amar kanas eino
motzi. So רב זוטי Rav Zuti taught a ברייתא Braita whatever according
to the position that if married you did not have to divorce,
you did not have to divorce. אמר להו רבנן לרב
אשי, Amar lei rabbanan l'Rav Ashi, so the rabbis said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, so גמרא או סברא. Gemara o svara. So when
this teaching that you רב אשי Rav Ashi say, which was רב
אשי's Rav Ashi position? Oh, he does not have to divorce. Is
that a tradition that you have or is that logical? Is that
something that you've derived logically? אמר להו מתניתין היא, Amar lehu matnitin
hi, which is sort of like neither. Okay, but I can figure
it out from the משנה. mishna Maybe that's סברא svara to infer
from a משנה. mishna Anyway, הנטען משפחה ונשתחרר מעבודת כוכבים ונתגייר הרי
זה לא יכנס ואם כנס אין
מוציא. Ha'nitan mishifcha v'nishtachrer m'avodat kochavim v'nisgayrer harei zeh lo yichnos v'im
kanas ein motzi. So you see these other cases, right, the one
exception was adultery, but these cases about not marrying because of a
conversion or whatever, things that you were suspected of an affair, בדיעבד
b'dieved if you get married you do not have to divorce. עלמא,
Alma, you see, בריננה לא מפקינן, B'rinana lo mafkinan, just because of
rumor and a concern, oh people are going to say, whatever, the
rumor is true, etc., we're not going to to divorce as a
based on those concerns. הכא נמי בריננה לא מפקינן. Hacha nami b'rinana
lo mafkinan. Here too we're not going to do it based on
those concerns of rumor. Now you can understand right
why these cases are not exactly the same. It's one thing the
guy marries the woman he was suspected of having an affair with,
right, who was a non-Jewish woman or whatever. What's the result of
the fact if the rumor were true? If the rumor were true,
he did something wrong and whatever, people think he did something wrong.
Okay. Here if the rumor was true, what's the rumor? Maybe the
husband isn't dead. Maybe the גט get isn't valid. So this woman,
you know, is an אשת איש. eishat ish. Okay, that's a pretty
serious concern. Now you understand why the רשב"א Rashba said that this
was only going on the case of the נדר, right, because the
case of the נדר even if the חכם Chacham. manipulated it, the
woman is still legitimately divorced. The husband still gave a גט get
to the wife, right?
So their case maybe at most a concern of rumor. But in
the case where the guy brought the גט get, or the guy
testified the husband is dead, you do not want there to be
doubts about whether the woman is legitimately divorced or widowed. So you
could really make a big difference between those cases. Yes?
I'm just in גמרא סברא, Gemara svara, is the quoting of a
משנה mishna the same as גמרא?
Gemara No, I thought it was the same as סברא. svara.
You thought there was סברא svara potentially like פסוקים? psukim?
No, גמרא Gemara, is like an oral tradition, you know, it's more
like the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai category to some.
It wouldn't be משנה Mishnah. then, that's what's so...
No, I don't know. No, I mean משנה Mishnah might be a
third answer, right? It's not just logic, but I think it's primarily
in the סברא svara answer. I think it's primarily the סברא svara
answer. Yeah. All right. Next, משנה. Mishna, וכולם שהיו להם נשים ומתו
מותרות להינשא להם. V'kulam shehayu lahem nashim umesu mutarot l'hinasay lahem. So
now this משנה Mishna finally, it does not deal with if they
married did they have to divorce, but it's a qualifying again, when
are we concerned that these people might be lying. So all these
people, the חכם who was not able to release the woman from
the vow, or the guy who brought the גט, get and all
these... or the guy who said the husband died, or he killed
him. If they were actually married at the time and then when
they, you know, delivered the גט get or when he said you
don't have to, I can't release you from your vow, and then
their wives died, so מותרות להינשא להם, mutarot l'hinasay lahem, then they
can get married, which is fascinating. So even in a polygamous society,
okay,
where polygamy is allowed, it was really a rarity, certainly in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael it was a rarity, and therefore and anyway when
it was done mostly it was only done by very wealthy men
who could support multiple wives. So therefore the משנה Mishnah is basically
assuming that at a practical level if a man is already married
he's not going to marry another woman. Okay, which is just fascinating,
right, because הלכה halacha, allows it but the משנה takes it for
granted that that basically won't happen. Therefore, if they're already married, we
do not have to suspect that they are manipulating everything and then
what? And then waiting for their wives to die? So you know,
now of course it is funny because you could say they're manipulating
and then they're planning on divorcing their wives, which could be done
unilaterally. Okay, but interestingly we're not concerned about that. If they're already
married, we're not concerned that they were manipulating.
Okay, וכולן שנישאו לאחרים
ונתגרשו או שנתאלמנו מותרות להינשא להם. V'chulan shenisu l'acherim v'nitgarshu o shenit'almenu
mutarot l'hinnase lahem. Also, if there is a somebody who interrupts, we
had this idea before about the case of that conversion and so
on. If they went ahead and the woman that you brought a
גט get and you said that this woman was divorced, you know,
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם B'fani nichtav uv'fani nechtam or that the husband
had died, and this woman married somebody else, and then the second
guy she married died or divorced her, then you can marry her.
Because since you're not marrying her immediately afterwards, no nobody's gonna say,
oh, you you faked the whole thing so she could marry another
man so then she could marry you. Right? If you really were
interested in this woman, you would not have wanted her to go
ahead and marry another man. All right, maybe. Anyway, we don't have
those suspicions if she married another guy in between. וכולן מותרות לבניהם
או לאחיהם. V'chulan mutarot livneihem o l'acheihem. Interestingly also, all of these,
the חכם and the guy who brings the גט get, can marry,
I'm sorry, not not the חכם. The women, all these women can
marry the brothers or the sons of the people that have caused
that have allowed them to be divorced from their husbands. Right? So
the guy bringing a גט, get, he can't marry this woman, but
the woman can marry his brother or his son. We don't assume
that he is manipulating and lying and falsifying for the sake that
a relative of his could marry this woman. All right, which is
interesting, you know, sometimes people do favors for their relatives. Okay, but
that we're not afraid of. So we're limiting the level of our
concern. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מתו אין נתגרשו
לא. Metu in nitgarshu lo. Right, so importantly, and this was the
point I raised, maybe the guy's already married, but he's planning on
divorcing his wife, which he can do unilaterally. So the גמרא Gemara
says actually that's a good point from the משנה. The משנה only
says that if he's married and his wife dies, he can then
he can marry the woman. But if he's married and he divorces
his wife, he can't marry the woman. Because then we could say
he
had it all planned. He was gonna marry this woman, fake a
גט, get divorce his wife, and then marry her. And it's even
better that way cause it looks more כשר kosher cause when he
when he gave the גט get, he was still married. So the
גמרא says, so מתו אין נתגרשו לא. Metu in nitgarshu lo. If
they divorce their wives they cannot remarry this woman or marry this
woman. אמר ליה רב זביד לרב אשי והתניא. Amar lei Rav Zevid
l'Rav Ashi v'hatanya. Wait a minute, we have a ברייתא Baraisa that
says, אפילו נתגרשו, afillu nitgarshu, that even if they divorced their wives
they...
אפילו נתגרשו, afillu nitgarshu, excuse me, אפילו נתגרשו, afillu nitgarshu, even if
they divorced their wives, they can then go ahead and marry this
woman. It's okay. So the גמרא says, לא קשיא. Lo kashya. It's
not difficult. הא דהוי קטטה הא דלא הוי קטטה. Ha d'havi ktata
ha d'la havi ktata. Was were they already fighting with their wives
or not?
Now which way is
it, which way does it go? So look at רש"י. Rashi, רש"י
Rashi
said what to me, I was assuming the opposite. Take a look
at רש"י, Rashi he said, הא דקתני אפילו נתגרשו, Ha d'katani afillu
nitgarshu, three lines into the גמרא in
רש"י, Rashi הא דקתני אפילו נתגרשו, Ha d'katani afillu nitgarshu, so אפילו
נתגרשו afillu nitgarshu they're allowed to marry the woman, כגון דהוה להו
קטטה. k'gon d'hava lehu ktata. I thought the opposite. The guys in
the middle of having a fight with his wife, there's marital stress,
then we could say, all right, he's planning on to marry this
other woman, he's planning on the divorce. No, רש"י Rashi, says that's
the case that it's okay. Why is it okay? Because רש"י Rashi
says, I know what you mean. So he says,
דאכתי לא נתן דעתו. d'achti lo natan da'ato. He says, look, if
they were fighting before he delivered the גט, get. then his plan
to divorce his wife was not in response to this woman. Okay?
Because he would have divorced his wife anyway.
Yeah, but no, but who cares? If she was in a state
where he was ready to divorce his wife for whatever reason, so
maybe he was manipulating this woman's גט. get It doesn't mean that
the wife's divorce had to be in reaction and started, the idea
came out about this woman. He was already planning or thinking about
divorce and then this woman shows up that he can manipulate a
גט get with.
No, that's not a manipulation. He was going to get divorced whether
or not this woman was going to come.
Right, which is why we shouldn't let him marry this woman. No,
but רש"י Rashi says we do let him marry the woman.
No, you should let him marry the woman, wait a
second, he had a terrible marriage anyway, whether this woman was going
to show up or not he was going to divorce. Right. Now
he has someone to marry.
He would have given the wife a divorce anyway.
Yeah, but that's a reason to think that he faked the גט
get, of this woman. You don't see it that way. Well, you
can defend רש"י, Rashi. okay. That's what רש"י Rashi, says. Okay. And
now if they weren't fighting beforehand, then we say clearly it was
all as a result of this woman. He saw this woman, he
wanted to marry her. He faked her גט, get. and then he
decided to divorce his wife and it all came as a result
of the woman. But if it started before this other woman showed
up, then we're not so suspicious. All right. איבעית אימא, Ibayis Eima,
איבעית אימא, Ibayis Eima, הא דהוה הא דלא הוה קטטה. Ha Dehavei
Ha Delo Havei Katata. They were not fighting in either case. Okay.
ולא קשיא. Velo Kashya. הא דארגיל הוא, Ha Deargil Hu, הא דארגילה
היא. Ha Deargila Hi. He was the one that was pushing for
divorce. If he was the one that was pushing for divorce,
don't re-marry the woman. If she was the one pushing for divorce,
then we could say, alright, then he was obviously doing nothing wrong
and because he wanted to stay married to his wife. So then
we don't suspect
what the delivery of the גט. get Of course, as the גמרא
says elsewhere, the way sort of interpersonal dynamics works in marriage works
is you can sort of get your partner to try to want
to get a divorce. So, alright, anyway, let's take a look now
as the גמרא continues. וכולן שנישאו. Vechulan Shenisu. Now
all if these women married another man, then they can go and
marry the first guy, the guy who delivered the גט get and
etc. סלקא דעתך, Salka Datach, מיתה מיתה וגירושין גירושין. Misa Misa Vegerushin
Gerushin. We assumed it meant that
there are two cases in the משנה, one is you testify the
husband dies and the other is
you bring a גט get, and then they go ahead and they
marry another person and this other guy either dies or divorces them.
So the גמרא says we were assuming that when you testify the
husband died, then she remarry a second guy, the second guy died.
Or when you brought a גט, get she married a second guy,
the second guy divorced her. Just
for parallel. So the גמרא says but that raises interesting questions which
is נימא מתניתין דלא כרבי. Nima Matnisin Delo Kerabi. This make it
not like רבי. דאי כרבי אמר בתרי זימני הוי חזקה. Dei Kerabi
Amar Betrei Zimnei Havei Chazaka. Another interesting discussion we're going to have
later in יבמות, Yevamos, a woman whose two husbands died on her
sequentially.
So she was married twice and both husbands died. Are you allowed
to marry this woman? Do we say that twice already is a
type of a חזקה, chazaka, normally we say three but two may
be a type of a חזקה chazaka that we say maybe there's
some reason why her husbands keep on dying on her and therefore
what, like black widow or whatever.
What, there was a woman whose husbands kept dying on her, would
you be third in line?
Well, but you want to. So anyway, alright. So רבי says don't
remarry. So maybe this משנה is saying you can remarry because that's
the scenario. So the גמרא says no, מיתה גירושין וגירושין מיתה. Misa
Gerushin Vegerushin Misa. We could say it was a mix and match.
The case where the husband died was then the case
where the case where testify the husband died then the second husband
divorced her or the case the husband divorced her then the second
husband died on her. All right. We'll worry enough about that later
on when we get to the discussion of רבי. Okay. וכולן מותרות
לבניהן ולאחיהן. Vechulan Mutaros Livneihen Ule'acheihen. And all these women can marry
the brother or the sons of the people who whatever brought the
גט get, and said their husband died.
So the גמרא says מאי שנא מהא דתנן, Mai Shna Meha Detnan,
or דתניא, Detanya, הנטען מן האישה. Hanitlan Min Ha'isha. If somebody is
suspected of having an affair with a woman, אסור באמה ובבתה. Assur
Be'ima Uvevita. You're not allowed to marry the mother or the daughter.
Why? Because if it was true that you had an affair with
that woman and then you marry the mother or the daughter then
you have slept with a woman and her daughter which is עריות
Arayos in the תורה. Okay. ובאחותה Uveachoso and her sister. So you
see there that we once there's a suspicion so we extend it.
So here too we say
that maybe now what exactly is the exact point? It's not exactly
clear because here we started with a suspicion you did something wrong.
So the issue really seems to be as I think רש"י Rashi,
says it, let me see the רש"י.
Okay. Yeah so it's important to understand the sequence because remember the
הלכה, halacha the איסור issur of sleeping with is not just a
woman and her daughter. It's your wife and her daughter. Okay. Or
the sister of your wife. So if you take a look at
רש"י, look at רש"י, אסור באמה ובבתה ובאחותה, Assur Be'ima Uvevita Uveachoso,
the second wide line. כדמפרש טעמא לקמן שמא לאחר Kedemafareish Taama Lekaman
Shema Leachar that's my weird bell I have. שמא לאחר Shema Leachar
oh gosh, I don't even know what's going on here. Okay. שמא
לאחר, Shema Leachar, כדמפרש טעמא לקמן שמא לאחר שישא את אמה או
את בתה תזנה זו עמו. Kedemafareish Taama Lekaman Shema Leachar Sheyissa Es
Imma O Es Bitta Tizneh Zo Immo. Okay. The real concern is
not that you already had sex with this woman and now you're
married to her mother or daughter. The point is you cannot be
married to a woman and then have sex with her mother or
daughter, but it only starts once you're married to the woman. Okay.
Is that clear? You have to first be married to a woman,
now you're married to the woman, don't have sex with her mother
or with her daughter.
So the
fact that you had sex
beforehand to a woman who wasn't your wife does not prohibit you
from marrying or having sex with her mother at another time.
Right. So okay. So let's take a look. כדמפרש טעמא לקמן שמא
לאחר שישא את אמה או את בתה תזנה זו עמו. Kedemafareish Taama
Lekaman Shema Leachar Sheyissa Es Imma O Es Bitta Tizneh Zo Immo.
ובזנות קמא לא. Uviznus Kama Lo. ובזנות קמא לא אבי מצר באימו
ובקרובותיה. uviznut kama lo avi metzar be'imo uvikerovoteha. וקיימא לן: ve'kayma lan:
נושאין על האנוסה ועל המפותה, nos'in al ha'anusa ve'al hamefuta, דלא נאסר
קרובות אישה על איש, delo ne'esar kerovot isha al ish, אלא אם
כן כנסה לראשונה, ela im ken kanasa larishona, דאישות כתיב בה. de'ishut
ketiv bah. Okay. So therefore, it's only once you're married. So whether
or not the concern is not that the now that you're marrying
mother or daughter or sister, that's going to be an איסור. issur.
The concern is you marry mother or daughter or sister and you
figure hey, I've got an idea, I'll marry her mother, and then
when the daughter comes over for a visit, I'll be able to
continue my affair with the daughter. So the reason we don't allow
when there's a suspicion of this affair to marry mother or daughter
or sister is because we're afraid that then because family stays together,
you'll have opportunity and you'll do it once it really becomes an
איסור עריות issur arayos and it will lead to it. Okay, so
here too the גמרא is saying I get that we're not afraid
you're going to sin just so your brother can marry this woman.
But maybe you're sinning for your own sake. You're going to lie
about this גט, get have your brother marry her, so that's a
nice sort of make it look all כשר so nobody will suspect
you. And then when you go to visit your brother, you'll find
opportunity to sleep with this woman. So why don't we have the
same type of a concern? So let's take a look. The גמרא
says, נשי לגבי נשי שכיחן דאזלן גברי לגבי גברי לא
שכיחן. nashi legabi nashi shechichan de'azlan gavrei legabi gavrei lo shechichan. So
the גמרא says, you know, women in the family spend more time
together. Mother and sister and daughter, so they visit each other. Right.
They visit each other. So if you're married to one woman, you'll
have opportunity to have some encounter with the mother or the sister
or the daughter. But, you know, brothers don't spend so much time,
don't visit each other so much. So if your brother is married
to a woman that you're interested in, you won't have so much
opportunity with her. All right. אי נמי, ee nami, the גמרא says,
or you could say נשי דלא אסרן שכיבותן אהדדי לא קפדי אהדדי
גברי דאסרן שכיבותן אהדדי קפדי
אהדדי, nashi delo asran shechivotan ahadadei lo kapdi ahadadei gavrei de'asran shechivotan
ahadadei kapdi ahadadei, another fascinating answer, which says if it were true
that if you actually slept with your wife's sister, okay, that would
actually not make you forbidden to continue living with your wife. So
therefore, she's not so מקפיד makpid if maybe you'll wind up sleeping
with her sister or her daughter, because it's not actually going to
make affect her marriage הלכתית. halachically. But if your brother's wife, if
you're interested in her, he's pretty מקפיד makpid because if you wind
up sleeping with her, then she's forbidden on him and then they'll
have to get a divorce. Again, quite fascinating, like really? That's the
level of difference here? Okay, אי נמי, ee nami, or you could
say אי הכי, ee hachi, the גמרא says, אביו נמי. aviv nami.
If that's true,
then why don't we even allow the father to marry this woman
that you brought the גט for? Why does it only say brother
and son? So the גמרא once these are not types of concerns
when a male relative is married to these women. גמרא says, you're
right, לא מיבעיא קאמר לא מיבעיא אביו, lo mibaya ka'amar lo mibaya
aviv, clearly the father can marry this woman, דבעית בריה מיניה, de'bayit
bereih mineih, that the father the son is embarrassed to, you know,
try to have an affair with his father's wife. Again, somebody before
was mentioning יהודה ותמר Yehuda ve'Tamar and those things, right, ראובן Reuven
and
יעקב, Yaakov, right. Exactly. אבל בנו דלא בעית אביו מיניה, aval beno
delo bayit aviv mineih, but a son's wife that a father might
not feel embarrassed because it's a son he feels he can take
advantage, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe we won't allow, קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that we do. So quite fascinating the idea here.
The concern is not some you're sinning for the sake of somebody
else. You'll only sin for yourself, but you want a relative to
marry so that you'll have an opportunity to continue to have an
affair. Okay. And the fascinating distinctions between men and women in this
regard which don't seem to be like probably, you know, factually true,
but at least the גמרא sort of teases as theoretical distinctions. Okay.
הדרן עלך יוצאת אשה וקרוב
אשת אחיו. hadran alach yotzet isha ve'kerov eshet achiv. Let's see if
we can get to at least the bottom of the דף, daf,
and the עמוד ב' amud bet is very small, so maybe at
least tomorrow we'll catch up a bit on that. But let's go
for it. ארבעה אחים, arba'ah achim, this should be familiar to you,
שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות. shenayim mehem nesu'im shtei achayot. So ראובן
Reuven and שמעון Shimon are married to רחל ולאה, Rachel ve'Leah, and
ומתו הנשואים אחיות, umetu hanesu'im achayot, and ראובן Reuven and שמעון die.
הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות. harei elu cholsot velo mityabmot. So now
you've got
לוי ויהודה. Levi vi'Yehuda. So they, we've done this multiple times, this
משנה we've already seen many times.
Okay, you can't see it too many times. You have ראובן Reuven
and שמעון,
לוי Levi and יהודה. Okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון were married to
רחל ולאה, Rachel ve'Leah, sisters.
They both die. Okay, לוי Levi cannot do יבום yibum with רחל
Rachel because רחל Rachel is, anybody?
אחות זקוקה, achot zekuka, right, there's זיקה zika both ways. So and
same with יהודה, so they can't do it. So all they can
do is חליצה. chalitza. Now after he's done חליצה chalitza with רחל,
Rachel, why not go ahead and then do... יבום yibum with לאה,
Leah, לאה Leah is no longer אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato רחל Rachel
is no longer זיקה zika because לאה, Leah, if she is not
going to be אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato becomes אחות חלוצתו, achot chalutzato,
okay? So either there is a זיקה zika here, and if he
gets rid of the זיקה, zika, it is a חליצה. chalitza. And
either way, זיקה zika is quasi-marriage, חליצה chalitza is quasi-divorce, so he
cannot do יבום yibum with לאה Leah because he is either having
sex with the woman he is quasi-married with the sister of the
woman he is either quasi-married to or quasi-divorced from. Okay, and the
same is true with יהודה. Okay, so they each have to do
חליצה chalitza to them both,
so חליצה chalitza has to be done. They don't each have to
do it, but anyway, the women require you do חליצה chalitza with
the women.
Is it a דאורייתא? de'oraita?
No, no אחות חלוצתו achot chalutzato is certainly דרבנן. derabbanan. אחות זקוקתו
achot zekukato, a little bit vague. All right, so anyway, הרי אלו
חולצות ולא מתייבמות. harei elu cholsot velo mityabmot. Similar to the theme
before which we had, you know, digressed from. If they actually went
ahead and went through it, יוציאו. yotsiu. They have to get divorced
because that was a real issue of, he went ahead and he
had יבום. yibum. That was a real issue about אחות זקוקתו, achot
zekukato you know, and if the אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato, by the
way is a דאורייתא de'oraita problem and then she is really דאורייתא
de'oraita not able to marry her, that actually makes it worse, that
makes it אשת אח, eshet ach, that makes it an ערוה דאורייתא.
ervah de'oraita. Okay, so they have to get divorced. רבי אליעזר אומר
בית שמאי אומרים יקיים. Rabbi Eliezer omer Beit Shammai omrim yekayem. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai actually says, no, בדיעבד bedi'avad maybe it was only
a דרבנן derabbanan problem, בדיעבד bedi'avad you can keep the marriage. ובית
הלל אומרים יוציאו. uBeit Hillel omrim yotsiu. Okay. היתה אחת מהן אסורה
עליו על האחד איסור ערוה,
hayeta achat mehen asura alav al
ha'echad issur ervah, אסור בה ומותר באחותה. asur bah umutar be'achotah. If
רחל Rachel was לוי's Levi sister, then רחל Rachel is not זקוקתו.
zekukato. So then he is free to do יבום yibum with לאה,
Leah, then רחל Rachel gets out of the picture. Okay,
איסור ערוה, issur ervah, okay now,
והשני אסור בשתיהן. vehashani asur bishteihen. But for יהודה, they are both,
he both of them are זקוקתו, zekukato, neither of them is an
ערוה ervah to him, so he still has to, he cannot do
יבום yibum with either. איסור מצוה ואיסור קדושה. issur mitzvah ve'issur kedushah.
Let's say רחל Rachel was אסור asur to לוי, Levi, not as
his daughter but let's say it was like an איסור דרבנן, issur
derabbanan, right? One of those שניות. shniyot. Or it was like, you
know, a case of I don't know, some איסור issur like a
כהן גדול kohen gadol and an אלמנה. almanah. Okay, so in that
case, that case is not strong enough, certainly not the דרבנן, derabbanan,
but even just the איסור לאו, issur lav, if it is not
a real ערוה, ervah, is not enough to remove זיקה. zika. So
even though he cannot consummate with רחל Rachel for these additional reasons,
she still remains זקוקתו. zekukato. So
היתה אחת מהן אסורה על זה
איסור ערוה, hayeta achat mehen asura al zeh issur ervah, איסור מצוה
ואיסור קדושה, issur mitzvah ve'issur kedushah, חולצת ולא מתייבמת. cholsat velo mityabemet.
Then he has to do חליצה chalitza with her, the only thing
that removes the זיקה zika from רחל Rachel is a real איסור
ערוה. issur ervah. היתה אחת מהן אסורה על זה איסור ערוה והשניה
אסורה על זה איסור ערוה. hayeta achat mehen asura al zeh issur
ervah vehashniya asura al zeh issur ervah. רחל Rachel is לוי's Levi
daughter, לאה Leah is יהודה's daughter. So in that type of a
case, right? So if רחל Rachel is לוי's Levi daughter, רחל Rachel
is out of the picture for לוי, Levi, he can do יבום
yibum with לאה, Leah, and if לאה Leah is יהודה's daughter, she
is out of the picture for יהודה, frees him to do יבום
yibum with רחל.
Rachel. ראובן ושמעון Reuven uShimon marry their nieces.
Yeah.
האסורה לזה מותרת לזה והאסורה לזה מותרת לזה. ha'asura lazeh muteret lazeh
veha'asura lazeh muteret lazeh. The one that is forbidden to one is
permissible to the other and vice versa. וזו היא שאמרו, vezo hi
she'amru, and this is what they said, אחותה כשהיא יבמתה. achotah keshe'hi
yevamtah. If you have an ערוה ervah that is the woman here,
רחל Rachel is לאה's Leah sister and her sister-in-law, right? That is
this case, sister and sister-in-law. אחותה כשהיא יבמתה, achotah keshe'hi yevamtah, if
one of them is an ערוה, ervah, then the הלכה is או
חולצת או מתייבמת. o cholsat o mityabemet. So the one who is
the sister of the ערוה ervah can either have חליצה chalitza or
יבום. yibum. If one of them is an ערוה, ervah, she is
out of the picture and the sister sister-in-law can do חליצה chalitza
or יבום. yibum. Just read the line in the גמרא, שמע מינה
יש זיקה דאי אין זיקה מכדי. shma mina yesh zika de'ei ein
zika mikdi. Obviously it is a problem of זיקה, zika, אחות זקוקתו,
achot zekukato. because if not, let us take a look. הני מתרי
בתי קאתו, hanei mitrei batei ka'atu, they are coming from two separate
households, right? So it is not a צרה tzarah case. So האי
ליבם חד והאי ליבם חד. hai liyabbem chad vehai liyabbem chad. Why
does not, not ראובן, Reuven, לוי Levi with one and יהודה with
the other? The only problem here as we have been describing is
this idea of אחות זקוקתו. So the גמרא says so you see
that is what is going on. So גמרא says no, לעולם אימא
לך אין זיקה. le'olam eima lach ein zika. So what is the
problem? משום דקסבר אסור לבטל מצות יבמין. mishum dekasavar asur levatel mitzvat
yevamin. So now we have seen that is a very far-fetched explanation.
Let us just read it again. דעד מיבם חד מיית אידך. de'ad
meyabbem chad mayit idach. Not really there is no idea of זיקה.
zika. לוי Levi really could do יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. Okay,
he says the connection with לאה Leah is insignificant. But what is
going to happen? While לאה Leah now is waiting, now he cannot
do it with both רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, they are sisters.
So לאה Leah has to wait for יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza
with יהודה. While she is waiting, יהודה dies. So it caused in
a case that she was some either יבום yibum or... It was
necessary and the circumstances didn't allow it. But if לוי *Levi* does
חליצה *chalitzah* with רחל *Rachel*, then even if יהודה *Yehuda* dies, he
can go ahead and do חליצה *chalitzah* with לאה *Leah*. So we
don't allow יבום *yibum* because it'll limit, it might lead to a
case where לאה *Leah* doesn't wind up getting יבום *yibum* or חליצה
*chalitzah*. Very far-fetched explanation. Let's just read it, and we'll end with
that for today. עד דיהבי בחד מיית אידך *Ad d'yavei b'chad meis
idach*.
When while לוי *Levi* does יבום *yibum* with one, then the other
יהודה *Yehuda* would die, וקא מבטל מצות יבמים *ve'ka mevatel mitzvat yabmim*,
and then the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum* would fall by the
wayside. Okay, so we will pick up with this משנה *mishna* tomorrow.